This is a picture of a sunset on Mars
هذه صورة لغروب الشمس على المريخ
taken by NASA's Curiosity rover in 2013.
أخذتها ناسا كريوستي روفر عام 2013.
Mars is a very cold planet,
المريخ كوكب بارد جداً.
flooded with high levels of UV radiation
تغمره مستويات عالية من الأشعة فوق البنفسجية
and extremely dry.
وجاف للغاية.
In fact, Mars is considered to be too dry for life as we know it.
في الحقيقة، يعتبر المريخ جاف جداً للحياة التي نألفها.
I'm an astrobiologist.
أنا عالم كواكب.
I try to understand the origin of life on Earth
أحاول فهم أصل الحياة على الأرض
and the possibilities of finding life
وإمكانية إيجاد حياة
elsewhere in the universe.
في أماكن أخرى في الكون.
People sometimes ask me,
أحياناً يسألني الناس،
how can you be an astrobiologist
كيف يمكنك أن تكون عالم كواكب
if you don't have your own spaceship?
إن لم يكن لديك مركبة فضاء خاصة بك؟
Well, what I do is that I study life
حسنا، ما أقوم به هو أن أدرس الحياة
in those environments on Earth
في تلك البيئات على الأرض
that most closely resemble other interesting places in the universe.
والتي تشبه بشكل كبير بعض الأماكن الأخرى المثيرة للاهتمام في الكون.
All life on Earth requires water,
كل الحياة على الأرض تطلب الماء،
so in my case I focus on the intimate relationship
وفي حالتي أركز على العلاقة الوثيقة
between water and life
بين الماء والحياة
in order to understand
من أجل أن أفهم
if we could find life in a planet as dry as Mars.
إن كان بإمكاننا إيجاد حياة على كوكب جاف مثل المريخ.
But since I do not have the 2.5 billion dollars
وحيث أنني لا أملك 2.5 مليار دولار
to send my own robot to Mars,
لإرسال الروبوت الخاص بي إلى المريخ،
I study the most Martian place on Earth,
إلا أنني أقوم بدراسة أكثر الأماكن المريخية على الأرض،
the Atacama Desert.
صحراء أتاكاما.
Located in northern Chile,
تقع في شمال تشيلي،
it is the oldest and driest desert on Earth.
إنها الصحراء الأقدم والأكثر جفافاً على الأرض.
To give you an idea of how dry it is,
لأعطيكم فكرة إلى أي درجة هي جافة،
consider here in Vancouver it rains over 1,000 millimeters of rain every year.
هنا في فانكوفر تمطر أكثر من 1000 مليمتر سنوياً.
In the Atacama, there are places with no reported rains
في أتاكاما، هناك أماكن لم تمطر بشكل متكرر
in the last 400 years.
في ال400 سنة الأخيرة.
How do I know this?
كيف استطعت معرفة ذلك؟
Well, because I was born and raised in the Atacama --
حسناً، لأنني وُلدت ونشأت في أتاكاما...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I had a unique advantage
لذلك كان لي ميزة فريدة من نوعها
when I started studying this desert.
عندما بدأت في دراسة هذه الصحراء.
So let me tell you guys a few fantastic examples
دعوني أخبركم بعض الأمثلة الرائعة
he has found
لقد وجدت
on how life has adapted to live with almost no water at all.
عن كيف تأقلمت الحياة بدون أي ماء تقريباً.
One of my first findings was in the entrance of a cave
أحد أولى إكتشافاتي كان في مدخل كهف
facing the Pacific Ocean.
يواجه المحيط الهاديء.
In this place, we reported a new type of microalgae
في هذا المكان، وجدنا نوعًا جديدًا من الطحالب
that grew only on top of the spiderwebs that covered the cave entrance.
التي نمت فقط على قمة شبكة العنكبوت التي كانت تغطي مدخل الكهف
Have you ever seen a spiderweb early in the morning?
هل سبق لكم أن رأيتم شبكة عنكبوت في الصباح الباكر؟
It's covered with dew,
إنها مغطاة بالندى،
so this microalgae learned that in order to carry photosynthesis
لقد تعلمت هذه الطحالب أنه من أجل استكمال عملية البناء الضوئي
in the coast of the driest desert on Earth,
في ساحل أكثر صحراء جفافاً على الأرض،
they could use the spiderwebs.
بإمكانهم استخدام شبكة العنكبوت.
So here they may access the water from the fogs
وهناك يتمكنون من الوصول للمياه من الضباب
that regularly cover these areas in the morning.
التي تغطي هذه المناطق بانتظام في الصباح.
In another cave, we found a different type of microalgae.
في كهف آخر، وجدنا نوع آخر من الطحالب الدقيقة.
This one is able to use ocean mist as a source of water,
بإمكانها استخدام ضباب المحيط كمصدر للمياه،
and strikingly lives in the very bottom of a cave,
وبشكل غريب تتمكن من العيش في قاع الكهف،
so it has adapted to live with less than 0.1 percent
وبذلك تكيفت لتعيش بأقل من 0.1 %
of the amount of light that regular plants need.
من كمية الضوء التي تحتاجها النباتات العادية.
These type of findings suggest to me that on Mars,
هذا النوع من الاكتشافات تقترح لي أننا قد نجد على المريخ،
we may find even photosynthetic life inside caves.
التمثيل الضوئي بداخل الكهوف.
And by the way, that's me.
بالمناسبة، هذا أنا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, for almost 15 years this region of Yungay, discovered by NASA,
الآن، لما يقارب ال15 سنة هذه المنطقة من يونغاي، التي اكتشفتها ناسا،
was thought to be the driest place of this desert,
كان يُعتقد أنها أكثر الأماكن جفافاً في هذه الصحراء،
but I knew that it was not.
ولكنني أعلم أنها لم تكن كذلك.
How? You already know the answer.
كيف؟ أنتم تعرفون الجواب مسبقاً.
Because I was born and raised in this desert.
لأنني وُلدت ونشأت في هذه الصحراء.
So I remembered that I usually see fogs in Yungay,
وأتذكر رؤية الضباب في يونغاي،
so after setting sensors in a number of places,
وبعد وضع أجهزة استشعار في عدد من الأماكن،
where I remember never seeing fogs or clouds,
حيث لا أتذكر أبداً رؤية ضباب أو غيوم،
I reported four other sites much drier than Yungay,
أبلغتُ عن أربعة مواقع أخرى أكثر جفافا من يونغاي،
with this one, María Elena South,
وهذا المكان، ماريا ايلينا الجنوبية،
being the truly driest place on Earth,
هو بالفعل المكان الأكثر جفافاً على الأرض،
as dry as Mars,
جاف تماماً كالمريخ،
and amazingly, just a 15-minute ride
وعلى نحو مثير للدهشة، تبعد 15 دقيقة
from the small mining town where I was born.
من مدينة التعدين الصغيرة حيثُ وُلدت.
Now, in this search, we were trying to actually find the dry limit
في هذا البحث، كنا نحاول معرفة حد الجفاف
for life on Earth,
للحياة على الأرض،
a place so dry that nothing was able to survive in it.
منطقة جافة جداً حيث لا يمكن لأي شيء أن يعيش.
But even here, well hidden underground,
لكن حتى هنا، في منطقة مخبأة جيداً،
we found a number of different microorganisms,
وجدنا عددا من الكائنات الحية الدقيقة،
which suggested to me that similarly dry places, like Mars,
وذلك اقترح لي أن أماكن جافة مماثلة، كالمريخ،
may be inhabited.
قد تكون مأهولة.
We even have some preliminary evidences
ولدينا أدِلة أولية
that these microorganisms may still be active
أن هذه الكائنات الحية الدقيقة قد تكون نشطة
in the desiccated state,
في حالة الجفاف،
like walking mummies all around us,
مثل المومياءات من حولنا،
and that they may be using UV radiation as a source of energy.
وأنها قد تستخدم الأشعة فوق البنفسجية كمصدر للطاقة.
If confirmed, this would have a huge impact on our definition of life,
وإذا تأكد ذلك، فإن ذلك سيكون له تأثير كبير على تعريفنا لكلمة حياة،
on how we look for life elsewhere in the universe.
في كيفية البحث عن الحياة في أماكن أخرى في الكون.
Due to its clear skies, by 2020,
بسبب سمائها الصافية، بحلول عام 2020،
60 percent of the biggest telescopes on Earth
60% من أكبر التلسكوبات على الأرض
will be located in the Atacama,
سيتم وضعها في أتاكاما،
and while everyone else will be looking among the stars
وفي حين أن الجميع سيبحثون بين النجوم
to answer the question, "Are we alone?"
للإجابة على السؤال "هل نحن وحيدون في الكون؟"
I will be looking down to the ground
سأقوم أنا بالنظر إلى الأرض
searching for this same answer
بحثاً عن نفس السؤال
in my own backyard.
في فنائي الخلفي الخاص.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)